So this is something I've changed my mind
on in the last six months.
I think the first thing we want to do
is accrue goodwill.
So I never really knew what I
was doing for [beep] years, but it
was accruing
goodwill. I knew that
if I put out helpful content for years on
end, that when I
did have a business and offering,
an email list, whatever it was,
that someone
would be,
maybe through the law of reciprocity,
in a position to give back.
I believe that most people bought my first
book, not because they wanted to read
it,
but they'd potentially had so many of
their thoughts challenged and changed
from my content, that it was a no-brainer.
It was the person
that you don't really know at a wedding
that bought you a drink,
and you feel obliged to go find
that person and buy them a drink back.
Mm-hmm.
So if you can accrue goodwill,
you're not going to get that from posting.
And I use personal training because it's
one of the easiest and
most common businesses I work within,
but you can apply this to whatever it is.
Taking pictures of your lunch won't accrue
goodwill.
Showing people the workout you did today
won't accrue goodwill.
You showing off that you're flying in
business class will not accrue goodwill.
Although you might misinterpret what other
people are putting online, which is
maybe actually trying to establish
authority.
So especially in the entrepreneurial
space, you take a picture of your car,
you're
establishing authority.
You do a video in your car with a Porsche
emblem behind
you, you're establishing authority.
That is not what you do in the beginning
of a social media strategy.
Now,
the best way you can accrue goodwill
is to solve problems.
Now, I can often see where people
are out of touch with their audience
when they
don't understand their problems.
I've got a coach at the moment called
Louis, and in that, he's under the
belief that if 100 people walk down the
street and he was to interview them,
that 95% of them want to feel better
and build a bit of
muscle. And I said to him,
"I think you're out of touch with the fact
of how many
people actually want to lose fat,
how many people are crippled with their
self-esteem, whatever."
If you don't understand the problems
that your client is
facing,
you will be so out of touch with accruing
goodwill with an audience.
Most people,
or actually most successful businesses,
are in the realm of solving
problems.
I know that's been said a thousand times
before, but you really need to
understand who your avatar is,
which brings me in.
And I know that every marketing guru talks
about avatar, but I'm not
looking at bright blue men.
Think about it even
when you look at adverts on TV.
If you're looking for an advert for a
pickup truck, it's,
"Get down to your local
Toyota dealership
and take out the new Hilux for a spin." If
it's an advert for more expensive cars,
"And the Porsche 911,
992 is going..." They even talk in the
absence of the audience that they're
trying to create and win over.
If you can talk to your avatar, you will
attract them. Do not try
and be someone that you're not,
because I did this for
years in corporate, and then
when I started personal training,
I tried to be a
corporate personal trainer,
and I attracted [beep] .
So your avatar,
make sure you know who it is
that you want to work with.
And again, be realistic with this.
Some coaches want to work with athletes.
Okay,
this is the worst [beep] of what we could
go after.
If we look at the UK population,
14% to 16% have a gym
membership. Go to your local gym,
your Pure Gym, your David Lloyd.
How many of them are [beep] athletes?
Nearly none.
And if they are athletes,
they're in sports clubs
or they're in academies.
And if they're in sports clubs
and academies,
they already have an S&C coach.
Some people are going after what they
want, not what the market actually is.
That is not a legitimate problem.
There are not many athletes out there
that need
S&C, and if they do,
they're not going to get it from a PT.
They're going to get it from an S&C coach.
And if they're good at what they do,
they would have been taken up by a sports
club.
So you need to make sure those problems
genuinely exist, and they're
not what you think the problems are.
They are actual problems.
Now, this is where experience
is a really valuable
commodity. So if you can,
even in the short term, let's say
one of the lads here today was, "Oh,
James,
I want to go into the coaching world.
I know how to make content,
do this," I would still say to them to do
at least one
to two years on the gym floor.
Maybe you only earn £30 an hour, but
if you can
accrue so much experience of your avatar,
that that can go so far in life.
I did five years on the gym floor doing
one-to-one.
So I accrued maybe,
actually a little bit less than that.
I did about 5,000 hours of personal
training, it was about three and a half,
four
years. Those years looking back
are the least amount of money I've ever
earned, but
I got to understand people so well
that that painted a path for the next
seven
years.
It's all their excuses,
the reason they're really not doing it.
All want to build muscle,
but they're not doing it for X reason,
X reason, X
reason.
You figured it all out by doing that.
And some of my highest paying clients,
they came in with their goals, and three
months in they're not making progress.
Mm-hmm.
I'd be like, "Be real with me. Why
are you here?"
Mm-hmm.
"Is it that exercising purely makes you
feel better?
Is it..." And they just go,
"Do you know what, James?
I do a bottle of wine a night.
By coming here in the morning,
it makes me feel like
I'm not going to have a heart attack."
Great.
Because now I'm not resenting you as a
client that doesn't make progress.
You were just bullshitting me.
Mm-hmm.
So then when I did move into, say,
an online service offering, I had the
experience to really understand what those
problems were.
Mm-hmm.
So our content strategy must surround
solving problems.
And some people sit here,
they've got a content block,
"I don't know what to talk
about." I'll literally say,
"List 10 problems."
And it sounds really reductive.
So let's imagine for the second
that the person here is,
their problems are
can't grow a following. We won't do 10,
that may be a bit too many, but we'll pick
three, for instance. Out of your avatar,
what would you say some of the problems
are they have?
Can't make ends meet.
Can't make ends meet. And another one?
Lacking the motivation to go and do it.
They don't think they have enough
knowledge to go and do it.
Cool.
This one's an interesting one because I've
already got an idea for this one.
But then people go, "Okay,
well let's go into the content creation
side of it." You
have a hook in the problems
that people face. Can't grow a following.
I'm saying,
"If you're struggling to grow your
following, then maybe you should try
this."
Mm-hmm.
I don't like at the moment,
I don't know how much of this you might
have done.
I hate it when people go, "These
are five things that we can do." I just
don't like
that.
Mm-hmm.
I don't like people numbering what they're
doing.
"These are three ways to lose fat." It
kind of is a bit of a disjointed story
arc.
I'd rather people just went straight into,
"If you can't grow the following, it's
probably because of this. And
if you do this,
you have a story how it works.
Oh, and did you know
that one of the biggest issues...?"
That will resonate with
people.
By the way, I completely agree with that.
When I first started the content I
was doing five years ago,
I started with like,
"These are the five ways to raise money."
And it was because I'd read [chuckles] it
was a formulaic way of getting people to
watch the video right to the end, right?
And instead,
I think the better way for people to think
about it is, why do you
want to raise money?
[chuckles] Ask the audience to engage with
you,
to learn why
do they even need to raise money?
They've watched "Dragon's Den," they think
they
need to raise money because that's the
only business show they've ever watched.
So they think raising money
is the way to build a business.
So it's like actually getting to the root,
back to your point of what is the actual
problem you're trying to solve for the
people you're serving, as opposed
to just following a formulaic thing that's
going to get you views for the sake of
it.
And there's another technique here.
I learned this from Ed Lawrence.
He calls it the dangle.
So say you've got three points.
Say your first point,
and just before you get into your second
point, talk about
the third point. So you go,
"Today we're going to talk about how to
grow your
following.
But just before we talk about how to get
over the fact that you lack
motivation,
we're going to look at how you can make
ends meet."
Oh.
So you can actually show them what's to
come with a preview,
similarly to what they
do on TV.
"And after the break we're going to
see..." You're actually dangling what
is to come-
Mm-hmm
...
so that you're kind of opening a loop
that they need to close only by staying
and being retained. That means
that they're going to listen to two
because they
know already a little bit about three.
The important thing is here, when you
are trying to present people the...
Because people,
let's look at also their habits.
We're going to move into a second about
how important the first one to three
seconds is. Maybe not so much on YouTube,
because that one to three seconds isn't
the hook, it's the packaging.
Mm-hmm.
And they've already made a decision by
clicking on your YouTube video.
And actually,
probably your first 10 to 20 seconds
is going to pay off their
decision.
Mm-hmm.
It's important that we don't waffle.
"Hey guys, welcome back," any of this.
You've got one to three seconds to make
them realize that you understand their
problems. If you can't grow a following,
it's because...
If you can't make ends meet, this
is something that's really important.
When you say lack of motivation,
already I think of a creative here where
we can go
counterintuitive.
You don't lack motivation because
motivation is something that
comes on the way after you've already
started. Your problem is inaction.
So you can actually hijack that
and not give them the answer they want,
you give
them the answer they need. But if we list,
the more problems we list, these aren't
going to apply to everyone.
If you can't grow your following,
probably 98% of the
people on social media don't give a fuck
about their following.
But it's still important
that we say the right things so
that also the algorithms
that we're using within certain platforms
can understand who it is we're talking
to.
Because it's within their best interests
on platforms to serve content to the
right audiences that they want. So
when it comes to growing a social media
following,
the strategy needs to be problem-solving.
Because if you can solve someone's
problems, they will keep coming back, and
they'll probably subscribe